Finding Aid for Office Of New Students Programs (University of Michigan) records, ca. 1950s-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office Of New Students Programs (University of Michigan) records circa 1950s-2005, 1989-2000
University of Michigan. Office Of New Students Programs.
5 linear feet
97117 Bimu 2
Office designed to serve students new to the University of Michigan, including orientation program, university mentorship program, and welcome to Michigan program, as well as information and referral service for first-year students. Records relating to new student orientation program largely concerning diversity training and selection and training of counselors. Includes manuals, guides, and videotapes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were transferred from the Office of New Students Programs (Donor No. 8523 ) in 1997.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open to research without restriction.
The idea for the Office of New Students Programs (ONSP) was first proposed during the Fleming Administration by a task force concerned with how to revise the orientation program. The ONSP did not come into being until president James Duderstadt took office in 1988. President Duderstadt issued the Michigan Mandate in which he expressed a strong commitment to educating students about diversity. The Office of New Student Programs was responsible for teaching sessions on diversity during Summer Orientation. The students who conducted these sessions were called facilitators. The goal of the facilitators was to teach new students how to gain a greater understanding of prejudice and stereotyping and how they affect students' personal feelings. When this project first began ONSP contacted many other universities and sources such as the Anti-Defamation League to find out what materials they were using to teach about diversity. The ONSP learned that one of the means of education was through video. The ONSP continues to discuss diversity at orientation. The office currently maintains a web site where they answer general questions about the university and their office. The url for this site is <www.umich.edu/~orient>.
The Office of New Students Programs records consist of files relating to new student orientation program largely concerning diversity training and selection and training of counselors. The records includes manuals, guides, and videotapes and are divided into four series, Administration/Organizational Files, Evaluations of the Diversity Program, Audio-Visual Material and Publications. The Administration/Organization Files, Evaluations of the Diversity Program and approximately half of the VHS tapes from the Audio-Visual Materials series were acquired by the library in 1997. The rest of the material was acquired in a separate accession in 2007.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Office of New Student Programs.; University of Michigan--Students.; College student orientation--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Office of Orientation.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Multiculturalism--Michigan.; Multicultural education--Michigan.; Cross-cultural orientation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Office of New Student Programs.; College student orientation--Michigan.; Cross-cultural orientation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Duderstadt, James J., 1942-; Minorities--Education, Higher--Michigan.; Multicultural education--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Office of Orientation.; University of Michigan--Students.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Administration/Organizational Files 1987-1996
  Administration/Organizational Files (1987-1996) is the first series. The diversity training manuals document the creation of the diversity programs that the office sponsored. They contain records which explain what the goals of the diversity programs would be, and what the university wanted the program to accomplish. The correspondence is mostly between the Office of New Student Programs and other offices at the University of Michigan, such as the Office of the President. The files also document the selection process for program facilitators, and job descriptions. The fourth manual, the most recent, represents how information in the ONSP was kept after 1989. The manual lists facilitators for that year and what activities and programs they would be in charge of. The file also contains general correspondence. Two other files contain evaluations of the diversity program from students that went through the program. All of the comments are anonymous. The series also contains the speech "Towards a Truly Multicultural University" by Frances R. Aparicio, associate professor of Romance Languages/ Latino Studies at the University of Michigan. The final folder in the series contains a speech and a transcript from the network news program Frontline. The episode is titled "Racism 101" and focuses part of the story on the University of Michigan. In addition to the transcript there is a video of this episode in box 2.
  - Diversity Training Manuals 1987-1989, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Diversity Training Manual 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Evaluations circa 1987-1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1988-1996 (Box 2)
  - Guides for Training circa 1987-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Speech, "Towards a Truly Multicultural University" (Box 2)
  - Transcript from Frontline, 1988 (Box 2)
    (see also videos)
- Evaluations of the Diversity Program 1987-1996
  The second series, Evaluations of the Diversity Program (1987-1996), contains various types of responses about the diversity program. These responses include those from the facilitators that taught the program and those from students and parents who went through the diversity program. The largest part of this series are the final reports from the student facilitators. At the end of the summer each of them wrote an overview on the summer programs and described their reactions to the whole experience. Other forms of evaluations include questionnaires, surveys and comments.
  - Comments, Evaluations (Box 2)
  - Surveys, Questionnaires 1987-1996 (Box 2)
  - Final Reports 1991-1995, 11 folders (Box 2)
- Videos
  Videos (1987-1994), the final series, is comprised of VHS videotapes. "Diversity 1988" is an earlier version of the video "Commitment to Diversity." "Diversity Administration Introduction, Panel 1988" is an amateur an video taken of a training session on diversity. "Diversity Panel 8/6" is an amateur video of a question and answer session between the facilitators and members of the faculty. The tape also gives a good explanation about the diversity program. "International Perspective: A Global Look at Cultural Diversity" interviews students that are studying abroad and they talk about their homelands. The "Michigan Mandate" is a copy of former president James Duderstadt speaking to new students and expressing his commitment to make the University more diverse. "Racism 101" is an edition of the network news program Frontline. The program focuses on racism on college campuses. Part of it deals specifically with the University of Michigan and some of the racial incidents that have occurred on the campus. "Talk to Us" is the name of an amateur video of an activity that was part of the orientation. An acting troop named "Talk to Us" acts out skits about diversity which encourage the audience to interact with the actors. "Team 1 1989" is another amateur video. It documents many of the activities that go on during orientation, included a walking tour and games. "University of Michigan, Commitment to Diversity" is a production video that interviewed many students from diverse backgrounds. The students shared some of their experiences involving diversity at the university. "University of Michigan Student Orientation Version three" contains interviews of students who share their experiences involving diversity.
  - "Diversity 1988" (Box 2)
  - "Diversity-Administration Introduction; Panel 1988" (Box 2)
  - "Diversity Panel 8/6" (Box 2)
  - "International Perspective: A Global Look at Cultural Diversity" (Box 2)
  - "Michigan Mandate" (Box 2)
  - "Racism 101"-A Frontline special (see transcript in Administrative/ Organizational files) (Box 2)
  - "Talk to Us" (Box 2)
  - "Team 1 1989" (Box 2)
  - "University of Michigan Commitment to Diversity" (Box 2)
  - "University of Michigan Student Orientation, Version three" (Box 2)
- Administration/Organizational Files 1987-1996
  Administration/Organizational Files (1987-1996) series includes general administrative files documenting the organization and its programs. The diversity training manuals document the creation of the diversity programs that the office sponsored. They contain records that explain what the goals of the diversity programs would be, and what the university wanted the program to accomplish. The correspondence is mostly between the Office of New Student Programs and other offices at the University of Michigan, such as the Office of the President. The files also document the selection process for program facilitators, and job descriptions. The fourth manual, the most recent, represents how information in the ONSP was kept after 1989. The manual lists facilitators for that year and what activities and programs they would be in charge of. The file also contains general correspondence. Two other files contain evaluations of the diversity program from students that went through the program. All of the comments are anonymous. The series also contains the speech "Towards a Truly Multicultural University" by Frances R. Aparicio, associate professor of Romance Languages/ Latino Studies at the University of Michigan. The final folder in the series contains a speech and a transcript from the network news program Frontline. The episode is titled "Racism 101" and focuses part of the story on the University of Michigan. In addition to the transcript there is a video of this episode in box 2.
  - Diversity Training Manuals 1987-1989, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Diversity Training Manual 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Evaluations, cir circa 1987-1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1988-1996 (Box 2)
  - Guides for Training circa 1987-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Speech, "Towards a Truly Multicultural University" (Box 2)
  - Transcript from Frontline, 1988 (see also videos) (Box 2)
- Evaluations of the Diversity Program 1987-1996
  The Evaluations of the Diversity Program (1987-1996) series contains various types of responses about the diversity program. These responses include those from the facilitators that taught the program and those from students and parents who went through the diversity program. The largest part of this series are the final reports from the student facilitators. At the end of the summer each of them wrote an overview on the summer programs and described their reactions to the whole experience. Other forms of evaluations include questionnaires, surveys and comments.
  - Comments, Evaluations (Box 2)
  - Surveys, Questionnaires 1987-1996 (Box 2)
  - Final Reports 1991-1995, 11 folders (Box 2)
- Audio-Visual Material
  The Audio-Visual Material (1950s-2005) is comprised of photographic prints, slides, DVDs, VHS videotapes and a 16 mm film reel. The bulk of the photographs document the training the ONSP orientation staff. The slides also show orientation staff training as well as miscellaneous images of the University of Michigan New Student Orientation and various images of student life. There are several videos in the series which were used as part of orientation programs, most notably a number of videos about diversity of campus. "Diversity 1988" is an earlier version of the video "Commitment to Diversity." "Diversity Administration Introduction, Panel 1988" is an amateur an video taken of a training session on diversity. "Diversity Panel 8/6" is an amateur video of a question and answer session between the facilitators and members of the faculty. The tape also gives a good explanation about the diversity program. "International Perspective: A Global Look at Cultural Diversity" interviews students that are studying abroad and they talk about their homelands. The "Michigan Mandate" is a copy of former president James Duderstadt speaking to new students and expressing his commitment to make the University more diverse. "Racism 101" is an edition of the network news program Frontline. The program focuses on racism on college campuses. Part of it deals specifically with the University of Michigan and some of the racial incidents that have occurred on the campus. "Talk to Us" is the name of an amateur video of an activity that was part of the orientation. An acting troop named "Talk to Us" acts out skits about diversity which encourage the audience to interact with the actors. "Team 1 1989" is another amateur video. It documents many of the activities that go on during orientation, included a walking tour and games. "University of Michigan, Commitment to Diversity" is a production video that interviewed many students from diverse backgrounds. The students shared some of their experiences involving diversity at the university. "University of Michigan Student Orientation Version three" contains interviews of students who share their experiences involving diversity.
  - Photographs and Slides
    - Orientation Staff 1979-1982, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Orientation Staff 1984-1989, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Orientation Staff 1996 (Box 2)
    - Orientation Staff, c. 1999 (Box 2)
    - Orientation 1995 (Box 2)
    - Orientation 1999 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Orientation Photographs, c. 1972-c. 1995 (Box 2)
    - Orientation Slides 1964 & 1974 (Box 2)
    - Orientation Training Slides 1992 (Box 2)
    - Orientation Slide Show 1993 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Orientation and Student Life Slides, c. 1950s-1980s (Box 2)
  - Video
    - "Michigan Video Yearbook 1986-1987" (Box 3)
    - "Michigan Video Yearbook 1987-1988" (Box 3)
    - "Commitment to Diversity" 1987 (Box 3)
    - "An Introduction to Computer Resources at the University of Michigan" 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Racism 101" 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Diversity" 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Talk to Us" 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Welcome to U of M" 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Diversity Orientation" 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Student Orientation Video" 1989 (Box 3)
    - "Team 1" 1989 (Box 3)
    - "Commitment to Diversity II" 1989 (Box 3)
    - "Commitment to Diversity, revised" 1989 (Box 3)
    - "Student Orientation Welcome, James Duderstadt" 1992 (Box 3)
    - "Student Orientation II" 1992 (Box 3)
    - "Parent Orientation Show" 1992 (Box 3)
    - "Diversity Video Element, Jason Hackner" 1993 (Box 3)
    - "Diversity Video Element, Sarah" 1993 (Box 3)
    - "Diversity Video Element, Julie" 1993 (Box 3)
    - "Diversity Video Element, Claire" 1993 (Box 3)
    - "Diversity Video Element, Cesar" 1993 (Box 3)
    - "Parent Orientation Diversity" 1993 (Box 4)
    - "Michigan Mandate" 1994 (Box 4)
    - "Welcome Week" 1995 (Box 4)
    - "Student Orientation v. III" 1994 (Box 4)
    - "Welcome Week 1996 New Student Convocation", 1996 (Box 4)
    - "Parent Welcome Sessions" 1998 (Box 4)
    - "Towards an Inclusive University" 1999 (Box 4)
    - "New Student Convocation" 1999 (Box 4)
    - "The Role of Graduate Student Instructors at the University of Michigan" 2000 (Box 4)
    - "As the Planner Turns-Orientation 2001" (Box 4)
    - "The Role of Graduate Student Instructors at the University of Michigan" 2002 (Box 4)
    - "University Health Services-Serving Your Health Care Needs" 2002 (Box 4)
    - "New Student Convocation" 2003 (Box 4)
    - "Thurnau Professors" 2005 (Box 4)
    - "Street Interviews" 2005 (Box 4)
    - "Parent Orientation" undated (Box 4)
    - "What About Diversity?" undated (Box 4)
    - "Diversity Panel 8/16" undated (Box 4)
    - "International Perspective: A Global Look at Cultural Diversity" undated (Box 4)
    - "Summer Orientation" undated (Box 4)
    - "Them Changes" 16 mm film 1993 (Box 4)
    - "New Student Convocation" DVD 2004 (Box 4)
    - "New Student Convocation" DVD 2005 (Box 4)
- Publications
  The Publications (1956-2004) series includes a number of publications produced by the Office of New Student Programs, most notably the "Insider' Guide", the University of Michigan Student Handbook. The series also includes Parent Handbooks, as well as the "Rounding Out A2" handbook for graduate students.
  - Insider's Guide 1956, 1989-2004, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Parent Handbook 1989-2004, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Rounding Out A2 1977-1997, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Student Athlete Handbook 1997-2004 (Box 5)
  - University Policies 1997-2002 (Box 5)
  - Wolverine Planner 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1996-2004 (Box 5)